[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is Majjhima Nikāya 152, the development of the faculties, indriya, bhāvan, sūtra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, on one occasion, the Blessed One was living at Khajangala, in a grove of Mukhera trees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the Brahmin student Uttara, a pupil of the Brahmin Parasārya, went to the Blessed One, exchanged greetings with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: The best one then asked him, Uttara, does the Brahman, Parasārya, teach his disciples the development of the faculties?
[SPEAKER_00]: He does, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, Uttara, how does he teach his disciples the development of the faculties?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Master Gautama, one does not see forms with the eye, one does not hear sounds with the ear.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is how the Brahman, Parasārya, teaches his disciples the development of the faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha says, well, if that is so, Uttara, then a blind man and a deaf man will have developed faculties.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: According to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Impair your senses and you'll be accomplished in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, when this was said, the Brahmin student, Uttara, sat silent, dismayed, depressed, without a response.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, knowing this, the Blessed One addressed the Venerable Ananda.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ananda, the Brahmin Padasārya, teaches his disciples the development of the faculties in one way, but in the Noble One's discipline, the supreme development of the faculties is otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ananda says, now is the time to...
[SPEAKER_00]: He asked the Buddha to explain.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, now, Ananda, how is there the supreme development of the faculties in the Noble One's discipline?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Ananda, when a bhikkhu,
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Pali is just bhikkhu there.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Noble one's discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Noble one's discipline, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's already this sort of an opinion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I want to point that out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, yeah, noble one's discipline, but then he refers to a bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: A bhikkhu sees a form with the eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: There arises in him what is agreeable, or to say, there arises what is disagreeable, there arises what is both agreeable and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: There hasn't arisen in me what is agreeable, what is... or what is disagreeable, or what is both agreeable and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is determined, gross, or... and dependently arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gross?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... Not subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not... yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or... or lārikāṃ.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like gross or disgusting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is determined, dependently arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is peaceful, this is sublime, this is equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: The agreeable that arose, the disagreeable that arose, and both the agreeable and disagreeable that arose, cease in him, and equanimity is established.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, yeah, it's what we mentioned before, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about avoiding or trying to get rid of the sights, agreeable or disagreeable ones, by going beyond them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you go beyond them, not by developing new sights that you haven't seen before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like when people say, oh, you get into meditation, then you see things that you don't see.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you actually perceive things that you don't perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop meditation, you understand the nature of your sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you go beyond them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nature, Pali word for nature is dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pali word for things, it's dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding dhamma means understanding things.
[SPEAKER_00]: This thing is dependently arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understands that it has nothing to do with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's dependently arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's another way of saying he's arisen independent of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not arisen for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not arisen from my essence of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not its creator.
[SPEAKER_01]: A noble disciple, in a discipline of one, all they need to do is remind themselves of that whenever things arise and they'll become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is exactly what Mūla Parīhā Sūtra said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about what you perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finding the better perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about understanding the nature of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whether it's agreeable, disagreeable or neither, agreeable or disagreeable, you'll be equanimous in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no engagement with it of any kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, it talks, speaks about the ceka.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how Ananda is one, a disciple in higher training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: One who has entered upon the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which may make you think, oh, no, he's a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's talking about a sotāpanna here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: One in, one, a disciple in higher training.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was already talking, he was already talking about sotāpanna before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one who has entered upon the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to me, it sounds one who is actually a sotāpanna who is making efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who is on the way to nibbāna, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because one can have the perception of an arahant, again, like what Mūla Parīyā Sūtra describes, but he hasn't fully developed that very understanding of that perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say I have a perception of an arahant, it means understanding the perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when he says he perceives earth, patujana, but then ārya-sāvaka, he knows, he directly knows earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: He directly knows what he perceives, as in he understood the root of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understood it as determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, he might not now make further effort to speed up the results of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the one who does make the effort, who entered upon the way, who is basically partaking in nibbāna actively, through his efforts, that's the next one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says, here and under, when a bhikkhu, the disciple in higher training, sees a form of the eye, hears a sound, smells,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you develop nibbāna in this very life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, you need to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to surmount it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see it as arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, as determined not to do it with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, that's what differentiates Sotāpanna from, from Bhutujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then... Bhutujana would not have that peace of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's agreeable, disagreeable, he has no independent high ground on which he can stand peacefully and safely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna has that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, these things will still keep arising for the duration of his life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the symptoms of the illness will still keep resisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he wants to get rid of all of it, then he makes that higher training and higher virtue effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby, even that peace that he has, in regard to agreeable, disagreeable, he starts regarding it as, no, this is all not wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is all determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: He developed this passion towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when Sariputta said you should regard pleasure as pain and pain as a deadly arrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, so it's it's no more like pleasure and pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just pain and more pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, it's all disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just to make sure you have uprooted the slightest sort of traces of ignorance that has manifested to some subtle lusts and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how even anāgāmī will become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you take that as a blanket attitude that will then have to result in nibbāna for somebody who has the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, like taking a broad spectrum antibiotics, they will have to get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're cured from the illness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to wait and the body immune system will eventually make all the bacteria, whatever else is still flowing around, disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you take the strong medicine that you know works exactly right under the right conditions, you make that effort and you completely rid of any symptoms here and now as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, without the right view, without having developed the sign of the mind, without having went through the existential solitude by yourself, without distraction and breaking of the virtue, to arrive at it, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also how, like, sometimes, you know, people might struggle to understand, but from Bhattacharya's point of view, sotāpanna is almost seen like an arahant, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the difference is exactly in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a tremendous amount of peace that Sotāpanna already develops, by being free from illness, or in this case, by being equanimous in regard to agreeable, disagreeable or neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from Bhutujana's point of view, yeah, that's massive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, from Arahant's point of view, even that, he can actually abandon, through development of that higher training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through developing dispassion towards it, by seeing it all disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... and that's also... that's... that's how you can also understand why sometimes sotāpānas would need encouragement from the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, people often think, oh, it's automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right view, nibbāna, arahantship is just like automatic process or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Person who has become a sotāpāna, in this case, developed that equanimity in regard to whatever touches him,
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't get struck by the second arrow of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't suffer anymore from that point of equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when suffering arises, he doesn't suffer amidst suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many people will be content with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many sotāpannas will be content with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's already a tremendous amount of freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, from the... from the previous standpoint, all the symptoms, lingering symptoms, occasional annoyances and so on, it's nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's trifle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Really.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that... from that... and that's... that's the symbol of seven grains and Himalayas.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how little is left.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing left, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: But was it what... even that seven grains is still something left.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although you're already equanimous in regard to pain, pleasure and neutral, you should make the effort and develop this passion to adopt it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you set up on the way of the higher training that results in nibbāna, here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that's how sometimes they didn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes sotāpanna stays content with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, even Venerable Ananda, living by the Buddha, with the Buddha for like, I don't know, 20 years, he's attended this.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was perfectly content.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't mean that he was, you know, he was quite peaceful most of the time, probably.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only when, like, Sariputta died, that he was sort of got in mind, got clouded and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that, he might have lost, like, his faculties might have kind of got, he lost the clarity of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what he still couldn't lose is that high ground of equanimity, of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, all you need to do is just, when that phenomenon ceases, it's all there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he hasn't been suffering, even amidst the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vāpatujana would be completely distraught and overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, from Arahant's point of view, there is still a degree to be achieved.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you do so by regarding even those states of, okay, I'm, you know, agreeable can't touch me, disagreeable can't touch me, neither agreeable, neither disagreeable can touch me, and now that shouldn't touch me either.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop attitude towards that as disagreeable, as not wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you really, through and through, practice that disenchantment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he goes on to describe the arahant, and how Ananda is one, a noble one, with developed faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a bit of a tongue twister.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you hear Ananda when a bhikkhu sees a form with the eye, hears a sound with the ear, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: There arises in him what is agreeable,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: There arises what is agreeable, what is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: There arises what is both agreeable and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same like for all three.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not, like, oblivious to what's in front of him, as in robotic.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows, oh, this is agreeable, this is disagreeable, this is neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, none of that has changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says, if he should wish, may I abide perceiving the unrepulsive, then the repulsive.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abides perceiving the unrepulsive, then the repulsive.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you develop it, that attitude, then agreeable will be seen as disagreeable, and disagreeable will be seen as twice as disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can perceive what is disagreeable and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the agreeable and the disagreeable, as in it's less disagreeable on account of disagreeable, because you fully surmounted the whole domain of the determined, that which is determined as agreeable, disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see its basis, you see itself, you see that dhamma, you understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, if you wish to look at this aspect or that aspect, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're completely free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's a pleasant abiding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: It went beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if he should wish, may I avoid both repulsive and unrepulsive, abide in equanimity, mindful and fully aware.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abides in equanimity, towards that, mindful and fully aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: Repulsive and unrepulsive, it's basically really repulsive and slightly less repulsive.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is the supreme development of the faculties in the Noble One's discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: And He goes and says, what should be done for His disciples?
[SPEAKER_00]: What should be done for His disciples out of compassion by a teacher who seeks their welfare and has compassion for them?
[SPEAKER_00]: That I have done for you, Ananda.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are these roots of trees, these entrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meditate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do not delay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or else you will regret it later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go there, make the effort to understand the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't go there, make the effort to look at your nostrils.